now that we have discussed memory virtualization
let's briefly discuss I/O virtualization
so in general the hypervisor so here we are assuming
now it is directly working on top of the
hardware probes the devices at start up similarly
to what their operating system does when there
is no virtualization
and once this is done it can report them to
the different operating systems the guest operating
systems that it is running and of course we can
use the interrupt mechanism to make sure
the hypervisor wakes up and does that
necessarily emulation when each guest operating
system is trying to interact with a device
now for some devices of course you realize
the operating system cannot really take control
of the entire device so if you have one disk
and that is being shared with all the operating
systems you cannot really let the operating
system take full control of the disk because
parts of that disk belong to other or are accessed
by
other guest operating systems so for some devices
actually with virtualization what
you do is that you emulate the device in
different ways so for a disk for example you
actually create a file that is maintained
by the hypervisor and that is what is actually
used to store what the guest operating system
believes is storing on
disk it's beneficial because for example you
can initially create a small file and let
the file grow depending on what is being written
there by the guest operating system rather
than allocating right from the start the entire
space that the guest operating system
believe it has access to in the disk
when it comes to a network device for example
then you could have the emulation performed
by the hypervisor by actually having the
hypervisor acting as a switch so each guest
operating system can have a different
mac address and then the way in which the
hypervisor handles different requests
for the network card is by actually behaving
like a regular switch also for virtualization
of I/O operations we have here the hardware
coming to the rescue of the software
because as we mentioned several times at this
point sometimes it's beneficial to let the
guest operating system and the processes run
by having the guest operating system interact directly
with the hardware rather than
having a sort of hypervisor-in-the-middle setup
so this is supported by modern hardware through
this thing called single route I/O virtualization
which basically is provided
by having at the hardware level different
memory spaces different interrupts reserved
for each different virtual operating system
guest virtual machine
so basically each virtual machine can map
his own memory to the corresponding portion
of memory you have in the physical hardware and
then you can handle the different I/O
requests coming from different guest operating
systems directly at the hardware level